One of the biggest problems we have with
large language models is their knowledge
is too general and limited for anything
new. And no, dumping your documents into
chat GPT every time you want to use them
is definitely not enough. That is why
retrieval augmented generation is such a
huge topic when it comes to AI and it
always will be. It is a method for
curating external knowledge for a large
language model. So you can basically
make it an expert on your data, your
meeting notes, your business processes,
literally anything you want. Now the
problem with rag is that this curate
step where we're getting our documents
ready for our agent to put it in our
vector database, it can actually be very
difficult, especially when we don't just
have a bunch of ideal documents that are
in something like a markdown format
where it's raw structured text for our
LLMs. What if we don't have a bunch of
markdown? What if we have a bunch of
different file types like PDFs? Good
luck trying to extract the raw text from
this. Or word documents, even working
with audio files or video recordings.
How do we extract the data from all
these different file types seamlessly
for our rag pipeline? Well, that my
friend is where doc comes in. It is a
free and open-source tool I'm going to
show you how to use today to work with
all these complex data types so you can
properly curate your data no matter how
complex it is to get it ready for your
rag implementations. So we can actually
work with complex files like this. It's
not just raw text. We got tables, we got
diagrams, we have pages that split
things. We're going to be able to work
with it all. That is what Dockling gives
us pretty much right out of the box. So
right now I'll show you how Dockling
works and how you can get started with
it super easily. Very quick to get up
and running. I'll show you how to work
with different file types in Dockling.
And even at the end of this video I'll
show you a complete rag AI agent that I
built. It's a template available for you
right now that uses Dockling in the Rag
pipeline to work with the different file
types and even uses some of the chunking
strategies that Dockling gives us in the
library. So it really does help us take
care of everything in our rag pipeline.
And like I said, the data curation step
is the most important part of Rag
because it sets the foundation for
everything. So, Dockling is a Python
package. All we have to do to get
started is install it with PIP. And then
they have some examples, super basic in
their readme here. Plus, they have a
documentation page. And so, I'll link to
both in the description. Great resources
to get you started, of course, with this
video as well. So the third link I'll
have in the description is for the
complete AI agent that I have made for
you using Dockling under the hood. And
so at the top level of the repository,
we have the agent. And then within the
Dockling basics folder, this is where we
have a few use cases I want to walk you
through. So you have a super solid grasp
of how to use Dockling at quite a basic
level. So really simple scripts here to
show you how easy it is to work with all
of these different file types with
dockling for our rag pipelines. So we
will go through the features of dockling
at a high level and how to work with
these different file types and then kind
of a culmination of that will be this
rag agent that is using dockling under
the hood. And so this question right
here the answer actually comes from one
of the audio files that I have in the
documents folder. So what I'm parsing
here for my knowledge base is exactly
what I have in the GitHub repo for you.
Take a look at that. We got an ROI of
458%. I can confirm that is the right
answer. So that is looking really really
good. And I do even have the full rag
pipeline in this repo as well. Now I
will say if you want a more complete rag
implementation that is also using
dockling under the hood I am hosting a
workshop in the Dynamis community this
Friday where I'm building dockling into
the primary rag pipeline that I have as
a part of the AI agent mastery course in
the community. So if you are interested
in building productionready rag
pipelines and agents definitely check
out Dynamis. And the recording for this
Friday workshop with Dockling is going
to be available permanently in the
community just like all of the workshops
that we're doing every single week. So
let's start now with the readme that I
have in the Dockling basics folder. A
little bit of a progression that I have
mapped out for you so we can get through
the foundations of this pretty
incredible tool. Starting with a simple
extraction. We just want to take things
like the text and tables out of a PDF
document. That is the first script that
I have for you here. and it's based on
the basic example that we have in the
dockling documentation. So we have our
source, we create this document
converter object and then we convert the
source to a document. And so now we have
this object that we can export to
different types like JSON or raw text or
markdown. Markdown is typically
considered the best format for LLMs like
I said at the start of this video. And
so that is what we want to do. And take
a look at this. We have extracted text
from a decently complex PDF. Like I'll
actually show you this here. If I go to
this PDF, it's not trivial with all of
the code examples and diagrams and
tables that we have in this. That is
what we're extracting with just a few
lines of code in dockling. It is super
cool. And I'm pretty much doing the same
thing here. I have the path to one of
the PDFs that I have in this documents
folder. I'm creating that document
converter, converting it, exporting it
to markdown, and that's pretty much all
I display in the script. So, I'll
actually show you this right here. And
it handles everything with OCR under the
hood. So, we have object recognition.
There's quite a bit of machine learning
that's actually happening to extract
everything from the PDF, especially
because of little nuances you have with
PDFs with things like tables being split
between pages. We have to handle all of
that. And Dockling also has a lot of
functionality built in for you if you
want to customize the OCR process. So
there are a lot of different options
that we have for different OCR
solutions. Things like Tessact for
example. You might have heard of that
before. So there we go. This is the
complete markdown of our PDF. And we're
not extracting images or capturing or
anything right now. There are ways to do
that in Dockling as well, but it does
actually recognize it. Like this is
where we have an image and we can handle
tables. Like overall this is beautiful.
And it was pretty fast as well. Like
definitely less than 30 seconds to
handle this entire PDF. And so now this
data is ready to be chunked up and put
in our knowledge base for our rag agent.
We'll get to that in a little bit. All
right. Now, for the second example here,
I just want to show you how easy it is
to work with multiple different file
formats in Dockling because under the
hood, it recognizes the file extension
and it knows what to do to work with
those different file types without us
having to do that much more in our code.
And so now in our second script, take a
look at this. If I go down to the
bottom, I have a list of a few different
files that I want to extract from. I got
a couple PDFs, a word document and a
markdown just to show we can keep
working with raw text of course as well.
So we create our document converter and
then I have this function to process any
document and it's pretty short overall.
We can just call the converter.con
convert on that file path. We don't have
to specify what the extension is. We
don't have to specify a strategy. I mean
there are some options we have if we
want to customize things but dockling
can be so so basic and still work
extremely well and then we just export
it to the markdown and then that's it
and we just print the output of each of
these files and so I'll go ahead and run
this script as well. I'll pause and come
back once we have the process complete
for each of these files. And there we
go. We got our little summary here of
everything that it extracted from our
four different documents. And this time
I also set it up so that this script
outputs to a folder right here. So we
can quickly take a look at the outputs
from our different files. And so for
example the word document that we
processed. I can click into this right
here. We got our meeting notes. There we
go. Looking really good. And it's all
structured markdown. Take a look at how
beautiful these tables look. These are
perfect markdown tables that it took
from the Word document. And we have our
PDF for example. Even more beautiful
tables. And it recognizes where we have
images. like this is just so so good.
Exactly what we need to now chunk up and
put in our knowledge base. And I'll
actually show chunking strategies in a
little bit. But the next thing that I
want to cover with you here is working
with audio files. And there's a specific
way to handle that with Dockling very
easily as well. So using audio files in
Dockling does require a couple of extra
dependencies because we need a way to
pull a model to handle speech to text.
And so make sure you install FFmpeg.
I've got instructions depending on your
OS. And then also if we look at the
requirements in this project, I did add
OpenAI Whisper, which is an open source
tool. We're going to be using Whisper
Turbo as our speech to text model
completely locally. Everything here with
Dockling is local by the way, just
grabbing models from Hugging Face. It is
a beautiful thing. And so going to the
third script that we've got right here,
we have our audio path. And then we call
this transcribe audio function. And this
function is pretty basic overall. We are
setting up what is called an ASR
pipeline. And there are a lot of
different options that you can configure
for your speechtoext pipeline. You can
take a look at the dockling
documentation for that. I'm just going
with the defaults mostly here to keep
things simple using the whisper turbo
model. So I set up my document converter
just like we did when we were working
with textbased files. And then again
just like with textbased files, we call
converter.convert. And then we can
export the MP3 content as a markdown
document. That is the beauty of Dockling
is all of the different file types we're
working with, they all just end up as
markdown. So we basically have the ideal
documents folder here where everything
is set up as markdown ready to be put in
our knowledge base. And we have to have
this extra step of data preparation to
make that happen. But Dockling just
makes that so easy. All right, I ran the
third script off camera to transcribe
our about 30 secondond audio file. And
in total, it took 10 seconds and
outputed 576 characters. And 10 seconds
is not bad considering this is running
completely locally with Dockling. So
here is our transcript output. And then
of course I have it in the output folder
as well. And it even has timestamps here
for all the sentences that it
transcribed. You can disable this of
course if you want, but it is pretty
nice that we have this metadata to build
into our rag system for any of our audio
files. Very, very nice. And so, going
back to our readme here, the last thing
that I want to cover. Now that we've
gone over extracting from different file
types and seeing how easy that is with
Dockling, I want to talk about chunking.
Not only can Dockling help us with the
data extraction from our documents, it
can also help us with the chunking part
of our data preparation. And this is
crucial because we cannot just take our
document text once we have it extracted
and dump it in our vector database. That
is way too much for the LLM to retrieve
all at once with RAG. We can't just give
it the entire document, especially when
they are much bigger. What we need to do
is split our documents into bite-sized
pieces of information for our LLM to
retrieve. So, it gets just that
paragraph or that bullet point list,
whatever it needs to answer our
question. And there are a lot of
different strategies to do this
effectively because obviously the
challenge here is how do we define those
boundaries? How are we going to split?
Are we going to split right here? Like
this would be chunk one and this would
be chunk two or we going to split right
here. How exactly do we do that? We
definitely want to make sure that we
don't split in the middle of paragraphs
and bullet point lists for example. And
so that's what Dockling helps us with.
It's a pretty technical challenge under
the hood, but Dockling makes it easy
with a few different strategies that it
give us. And the one that I want to
focus on here that is getting insane
results for me is hybrid chunking. This
gets a little bit technical, but bear
with me because I think this is
fascinating and super powerful. With
hybrid chunking, we are using an
embedding model to define the semantic
similarity between the different, you
know, paragraphs and sentences that we
have in our document. So, we use the
embedding model to figure out where can
we split in this document to still keep
the core ideas together in these
bite-sized pieces of information for the
LLM. And because Dockling takes care of
all the logic of the strategy under the
hood, using it is actually pretty
simple. So, in the fourth script that I
have for you here, we have a path to a
PDF that we want to process. And so,
we're going to turn this into a dockling
document just like we've been doing in
our other scripts. But instead of
extracting the text from it right away,
we're going to create this hybrid
chunker object. There are a few
different parameters that you can
customize here. Once you have this
though, you just call chunker.chunk on
the document. So this is our PDF doc,
obviously. And so we're going to get an
output that is kind of similar to the
markdown that we saw when we ran the
first script, but this time things are
going to be split up in a way where we
already have our chunks ready to insert
in the vector database. Like literally
what we have as the output from this
script is what we can put right in our
vector database. So just like the last
example, I ran the four script off
camera to extract the text from our PDF
and chunk it with hybrid chunking. And
so in the end we have 23 total chunks.
13 that are between 0 and 128 tokens and
10 that are between 128 and 256.
And so we have some variety here because
we are allowing the embedding model
within reason. Of course, we have a max
token limit for each chunk. We are
letting the embedding model decide what
goes into each bite-sized piece of
information to keep all the similar
ideas together. And of course, I've got
the output for the chunks as well. And
this is looking so good. We have the top
chunk with the title and subtitle. We
have all of our sections together.
Bulletoint lists are maintained in each
chunk. This is super ideal. All of our
sections, as long as they're short
enough, they remain in a single chunk as
well. And this all comes from a complex
PDF. Like this is just a beautiful
thing. And then at this point, we can
take all of these chunks and insert them
right into our vector database. In fact,
that is what I have now as the top level
example for you here. And I'll cover
this in a little bit with you. This is
the complete rag AI agent that takes all
of these ideas. We're parsing MP3s and
PDFs and Word documents. We're using
hybrid chunking. We're getting all this
ready. And then I have an AI agent built
on top that can query it. And that's
what I demoed at the start of this
video. The last thing I want to say on
Dockling before I get more into the rag
agent is you should definitely check out
the example part of their docs if you
want to learn more. There are so many
great use cases they have built out here
and just showing you ways to customize
the platform. For example, custom
conversion. We can see how to use
different OCR backends for extracting
text from files like our PDFs. Also,
they have this visual grounding example
which is super super cool. Not only can
the agent reference knowledge in our
knowledge base that we have curated with
dockling, but it can also literally
highlight like draw a box over the part
of the document that it got its answer
from. Very, very cool. So, Dockling
really handles everything that we need
as far as data extraction. And so,
generally how I think about it is if I'm
dealing with website data, then I use
crawl for AI. I've covered this on my
channel before. I'll even link to a
video right here. for anything else
besides websites with any kind of
documents I'm dealing with, then I will
go with Dockling. So, these are the two
tools that I have in my arsenal to build
out pretty much any rag pipeline that I
want. And so, definitely let me know in
the comments if you want me to cover
more use cases with Dockling or even
showing you how to use in other
platforms like N8N. I definitely want to
keep covering Dockling in more content
for you. All right, here is the grand
finale because now we're combining
everything we learned around chunking
and parsing different document types
into a single rag agent that I have as a
template for you. Link to all this
below. And so right now I just want to
cover at a high level how this works and
how doling fits into our rag pipeline
and even show the agent and the tools
that I'm giving it to search our
knowledge base that we curate with the
help of dockling. And so this read me
that I have at the top level of the
repository. This has an overview of the
agent, prerequisites, a quick start,
including setting up your database and
all the tables that we have here. Really
easy to get this up and running yourself
if you want to use it and build on top
of it. And so we have our database
schema here. For the vector database,
I'm using Postgress with PG Vector. And
of course, you could tune this to use
Pine Cone or Quadrant. They even have
some examples with Quadrant in the
Dockling documentation. But yeah, we
have our document table here where we
store the higher level information like
each of the individual documents that we
have in our knowledge base. And then we
have a table to store all the chunks
that we create with the doc dockling
hybrid chunking strategy. And then we
have our match chunks function. This is
the SQL that our agent actually invokes
as a tool to search our knowledge base.
And so most of the logic with dockling
itself is in the chunker.py pi right
here because this is where we chunk our
documents. And so I have this function
here where we pass in that dockling
document. So this is going to be our PDF
or our word document. And just like we
saw in the simpler examples before, we
just call chunker.chunk on that dockling
document. That is all we have to do to
perform hybrid chunking. It is so easy.
And then we pull the contextualized
text. Contextualize basically just means
we're also including things like the
headings and subheadings that we have in
the markdown as well. And then we create
our chunk metadata. I could do a whole
another video on metadata as well, but
just providing that additional
information that speaks to our chunk.
And then we're just adding that to our
list of chunks that we're curating. So
we then take these chunks, we embed them
with an embedding model, and we store
them in our vector database. At this
point, there is no more document
processing we need to do because with
Dockling through parsing our different
file types and performing the hybrid
chunking, we now have our text in
exactly the format that we're now going
to insert in our vector database. Again,
regardless of the vector database that
you use and then for our AI agent here,
you know that I love using Pyantic AI if
you've seen any of my content
previously. So, we're using Pideantic AI
to create our agent here. So we have
some logic here to set up our database
connection because we're giving that in
as a dependency to our agent. So we've
got nice system prompt here and then
giving it a single tool to search our
knowledge base to perform a rag query.
And so I'll go to this function really
quickly here. Search knowledge base. We
just have a query that the agent decides
basically it's search for our knowledge
base. We set up the database connection.
We embed the query with the same
embedding model that we use in our rag
pipeline. And then we're going to call
that match chunks function that I showed
earlier. So we're passing in the query
here. It's going to return all of the
similar chunks that we have, you know,
compared to the user query and then
that's returned to the agent to then
reason about what it retrieved and use
that to help give us the final answer.
That is rag in a nutshell. And so going
back to our diagram here, we've mostly
been covering the data preparation, but
now I'm starting to speak to the
retrieval augment generation, the actual
query process that we have because we
create an embedding based on that query
that the agent decides that hits the
vector database to retrieve the relevant
chunks that we have curated from
Dockling. Then that is fed back into the
LLM to give us the final response. All
right, back in the terminal now, we can
run the CLI that kicks off the chat
interface with our agent. And I already
ran the whole ingestion pipeline here
that pulls all the documents and it
looks very similar to the examples we
saw earlier where it just pulls the text
from each of the documents, performs
hybrid chunking, puts it in our
database. So we've got our knowledge
base ready to go. 13 documents, 157
chunks in total, all processed by
Dockling. And so now I can ask it some
questions where clearly you'd have to go
to the knowledge base to get the answers
for us here. And this is all just mock
data for a fake company that I generated
for our demo purposes. And there we go.
The revenue target for Q12025 is set at
3.4 million. And I believe this is from
one of the PDF documents that we have.
And so on my lefth hand monitor here,
I've got some other questions like from
one of our Word docs. When was Neuroflow
AI founded? Let's make sure it gives us
the answer of 2023. Yep, there we go.
All right, looking good. Let's just do
one more question here just to test
something. Uh maybe from one of the MP3
files. So one of the MP3 files I talked
about global finance. What ROI did
Global Finance achieve? And it should
say, there we go. Yep. 458%.
All right. And each of these times is
telling us that it's using the search
knowledgebased tool that we saw set up
in the code for our agent and in the
database. So this is working
phenomenally. So there you go. That is
everything that I have for you today for
Dockling. And like I said, this is one
of the most critical tools for your rag
implementation for any agent or
application that you're building that
needs to bring external information into
a large language model. So definitely I
do want to cover Dockling a lot more in
the future, building out more specific
use cases with it, showing some of the
more advanced features like actually
captioning images that we pull from
PDFs. There's so many more things that
we can do with this tool. Dockling plus
crawl for AI is all you need for any
data you have to extract for any use
case. So if you appreciated this video
and you're looking forward to more
things on rag and AI agents, I would
really appreciate a like and a
subscribe. And with that, I will see you
in the next